International Union of Steam Engineers, Local 62 Records 1984.0008
Archives and Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
International Union of Steam Engineers, Local 62 Records
undated, 1901-1905
Archives and Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
1984.0008
0.1 Linear Feet
Labor union of steam-driven construction equipment operators of Danbury, Connecticut. Collection consists of correspondence, grievance reports, by-laws and constitution, and membership lists. Includes information about work conditions of the union members and a strike in 1904.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated by the Connecticut State Library in 1984.
Arrangement
Series I: Records (undated, 1901-1905) contains all the materials in the collection in one folder, arranged chronologically.
History
The National Union of Steam Engineers was organized on December 7, 1896. In 1898 the union became the International Union of Steam Engineers, and was affiliated with the American Federation of Labor. Local 62 in Danbury, Connecticut, was formed by 1901, originally as the Danbury Union of Steam Engineers.
In 1912 the union changed its name to the International Union of Steam and Operating Engineers, and in 1928 it became the International Union of Operating Engineers>, which it remains today.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of correspondence, grievance reports, by-laws and constitution of the local, and membership lists, with information about work conditions and a strike in 1904. Of interest are agreements between the Fur Hat Manufacturers Association and the Danbury Union of Steam Engineers made around the time of the famous Danbury Hatters Strike of 1902, when the striking workers of Loewe Hat Company in Danbury organized a national boycott of the company's hats in protest of unfair bargaining practices. The company sued the union, which was found guilty in 1908 by the U.S. Supreme Court of violating the Sherman Anti-Trust Act.
Much of the correspondence is to Irving E. Andrews, Secretary of Local 62, from the following union representatives: John E. Bruner, President of the I.U.S.E., writing from Cincinnati, Ohio, and Robert A. McKee, General Secretary-Treasurer of the I.U.S.E., writing from Peoria, Illinois.
Steam-engines; Labor unions; Connecticut (state); Administrative records; Correspondence; bylaws (administrative records); Financial Records; Danbury (inhabited place); Engineers; International Union of Operating Engineers
- Series I: Records, undated, 1901-1905
  - List of members of Fur Hat Manufacturers Association, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Blanks, Application for sanction to strike, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Blanks, Report of strike, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Membership cards issued to Irving E. Andrews, 1901, 1902 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letter from I. E. Andrews, secretary to the manufacturers in Danbury, to members of the Fur Hat Manufacturers Association in Danbury, concerning enforcement of the by-laws of the union, 1903 February 21 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Meeting minutes, 1903 March 5 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Agreements between the Fur Hat Manufacturers Association and the Danbury Union of Steam Engineers, Local Union #62, 1903 March 5 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letter from Harry Ryan to Local 62 charging another union member of using "underhanded means" to have him discharged from his position at the City Pumping Station, 1904 September 3 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letter to John E. Bruner, union president, concerning conditions between Local 62 and Grau's Hat Factory from unknown writer (typescript copy), 1904 September 15 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Report of Grievance Committee on conditions existing at the Bethel Manufacturing Co., 1904 October 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Circular letter from William J. Cunningham of the International Association of Tube Workers of America, Local Union No. 5 of Somerville, Massachusetts, to all Organized Labor, asking for donations to the local to help strikers, 1904 October 3 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Report of William C. Light delegate to Central Labor Union meeting, 1904 October 6 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Report of Grievance Committee on conditions at the Bethel Manufacturing Co., 1904 October 13 and 25 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Circular letter from R. A. McKee to all affiliated locals notifying them about new constitutions and dues owed, 1904 October 20 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letter from R. A. McKee toI. E. Andrews concerning his receipt of reports, 1904 October 21 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letter from R. A. McKee to I. E. Andrews concerning the power of a shop steward of the Hatters to examine engineers cards, 1904 October 21 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letter from John E. Bruner to I. E. Andrews concerning the matter of the shop steward, 1904 October 24 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Circular letter from J. F. McLain of Local Union 120, I.U.S.E. of St. Joseph, Missouri, asking for funds to help strikers, 1904 October 25 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - International Union of Steam Engineers General Secretary-Treasurer's Report for the Quarter Ending October 31, 1904, 1904 November 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letter from R. A. McKee to I. E. Andrews concerning receipt of order for supplies, 1904 November 7 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Circular letter from R. A. McKee to all affiliated locals, about notification that the new constitutions are ready for distribution, 1904 November 17 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letter from Orrin S. Barnum, Assistant Secretary of the Fur Hat Manufacterers' Association of Danbury and Bethel to I. E. Andrews making an appointment to meet, 1904 December 7 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Circular letter from R. A. McKee to all local secretaries that the General Executive Board has passed a ruling of charging new members a grand dues of $1.00, 1905 January 4 (Box 1, Folder 1)